Guide to the Walter W. and Ella F. Fondren Papers, 1838-1973 MS 390
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Walter W. and Ella F. Fondren Papers, 1838-1973
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Fondren, Ella F.
MS 390
7.75 Linear Feet (14 boxes)
The Fondren Papers provide a record of the Fondren family's acquisition and dispersal of money in Houston and across Texas during the first three-quarters of this century and offers additional information on the financial workings of several well-known institutions and corporations. Formats include correspondence and financial documents.
Biographical Note
Walter W. Fondren was born in 1877 in Tennessee, the son of a farmer, who moved the family to Arkansas in 1883. Orphaned at the age of nine or ten, W. W. Fondren began working on farms in Arkansas and Texas. Then in 1897 he worked as a helper on a drilling rig at Corsicana, Texas, developing rapidly and becoming an independent driller during the first decade of this century. While he was working at Corsicana, he met and married Ella F. Cochrum.
Born at Hazel, Kentucky, Ella Cochrum was in her mid teens when her father died, making it necessary for her to quit school to care for her sister and five brothers. She and Walter Fondren were married on Valentine's Day, 1904 in Corsicana, and soon thereafter moved to Houston, where a son and two daughters were born to them and where they lived for the remainder of their lives.
Mr. Fondren was elected a director of the Humble Oil Company, then controlled mostly by Ross. S. Sterling, in 1912. In 1917 the Humble Oil and Refining Company was formed, and Walter Fondren was elected vice president. He assumed responsibility for drilling on the Gulf coast when Humble was affiliated with Jersey Standard in 1919. When W. S. Farish was elected Jersey director (1933), while retaining the Humble presidency, W. W. Fondren retired. After several years of heart trouble, he died suddenly early in 1939.
The Fondren's interest in aiding worthy institutions led to the establishment of the Fondren Foundation in 1948 to manage the resources of an estate valued at over thirty-three million dollars at the time of Mr. Fondren's death. Prominent among the recipients of this generosity have been St. Paul's Methodist Church, Methodist Hospital, Methodist Homes for Older People and the YMCA, all in Houston and Southern Methodist University in Dallas. Mrs. Fondren's concern with health care and the training of nurses led her to charter the Texas Association of Hospital Auxiliaries in 1943. Over the years she also provided money for scholarships and awards for nursing students. At the time of her death in 1982, Ella F. Fondren had devoted much of this century to local philanthropy.
Scope and Contents
Walter W. Fondren performed a conspicuous part in the development of the petroleum industry in Texas. The considerable wealth generated by his success in this field was later, through the agency of Ella F. Fondren and the Fondren Foundation, made available to several civic, religious, and educational organizations, predominately in Texas. The Fondren Papers, occupying approximately 7.75 linear feet, provide a record of the Fondrens's acquisition and dispersal of money during the first three-quarters of this century and offers additional information on the financial workings of several well-known institutions and corporations.
The Fondren Papers comprise fourteen Hollinger boxes that include passbooks, ledgers, and other financial records. Books in a tin deed box (ca. 1890-1910) labeled with W. W. Fondren's card were reboxed but the box was retained. Constituted almost completely by correspondence and documents concerning financial matters, the collection is arranged in a single alphabet, the papers in each folder being further arranged in chronological order.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
The Fondren Papers were given by Doris Ledwidge Fondren, the Fondren's daughter-in-law, on October 13, 1983. A second lot of papers was given by Mrs. W. W. Fondren III on December 15, 1988, and integrated into the papers processed in 1986.
Related Material
Fondren Family Collection, MS 340, Woodson Research Center, Fondren Library, Rice University
Index Terms
Subjects
Academic libraries -- Texas; Young Men's Christian associations; Charities -- Texas; Farms -- Texas; Universities and colleges; Libraries; Petroleum industry and trade; Methodist universities and colleges; Education, Higher -- Texas; Ranches -- Texas; Real property -- Texas; Hospitals; Agriculture; Business
Document Types
bankbooks; corrrespondence
Places
Houston (Tex.) -- History.
Subjects (Corporations)
St. Paul's Methodist Church (Houston, Tex.); Fondren Library; Rice University; Southern Methodist University; Methodist Hospital (Houston, Tex.); Humble Oil and Refining Company (Incorporated in Tex.); Houston YMCA (Houston, Tex.)
- Series I: Alphabetical files, 142798
  - A: miscellaneous correspondence, 1931-1967; 18573 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abstracts of title, 1899-1909; 18572 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abstracts of title, 1910-1911; 18571 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Abstracts of title, 1911-1919; 18570 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Abstracts of title, 1928-1931; 18569 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Abstracts of title, 1932-1933; 18568 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Abstracts of title, 1933-1936; 18567 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Abstracts of title, 1949; 18566 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Abstracts of title, 1949; 18565 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Allday, Edwin: correspondence, deeds, titles, 1956-1963; 18564 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - B: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, titles, stock certificates, accounts, 1903-1965; 18563 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Barrett, C. E.: land titles, deeds, 1901-1908; 18562 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Baytown Hardware Company: correspondence, accounts, 1948-1956; 18561 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Brahman cattle inquiries: correspondence, 1945-1965; 18560 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - C: miscellaneous correspondence, 1913-1972; 18559 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Christian Rural Overseas Program [CROP]: correspondence, brochure, photos, 1957-1959; 18558 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Commerce Street [2301-2307] property, Houston, Texas: correspondence, titles, notes, 1930-1972; 18557 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Curiosities, [n. d.]; 18556 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - D: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, titles, stock certificates, 1910-1965; 18555 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Davis Hill Oil Company: correspondence, maps, 1935-1953; 18554 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - E: miscellaneous correspondence, 1930-1946; 18553 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Edwards Family land deal: titles, legal testimony, correspondence, 1887-1929; 18552 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - F: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, titles, 1930-1962; 18551 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Farm accounts and correspondence, 1940-1965; 18550 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fondren, A. L.: correspondence, accounts, notes, 1926-1936; 18549 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fondren, E. F.: will, 1939-1956; 18548 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Fondren, W. W.: will and estate, 1925-1942; 18547 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Fondren Foundation: correspondence, charters, 1955-1967; 18546 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Fondren Lectures, Southern Methodist University: correspondence, 1927-1931; 18545 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Fondren Oil Company: correspondence, accounts, 1907-1940; 18544 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Fondren Scholarship Fund, Southern Methodist University: correspondence, 1927-1948; 18543 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fondren Trust [no. 1]: correspondence, charters, 1928-1944; 18542 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Forest Park Cemetery: correspondence, deeds, plans, photos, 1939-1961; 18541 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - G: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, titles, 1918-1969; 18540 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - General Hospital Board, Methodist Hospitals: correspondence, 1931-1942; 18539 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Gibraltar Savings and Building Association, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1931-1938; 18538 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Green's Bayou, Harris County, Texas property: county survey deeds, titles, 1838-1904; 18537 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Gulf Coast Gross Production Reports, 1923, 1927; 18536 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Gulf Oil Corporation: correspondence, 1943-1968; 18535 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - H: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, titles, 1919-1971; 18534 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Harris County, Texas. Grand Jury report, (November term, 1927): 1928; 18532 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Hammett Oil Company: correspondence, 1924-1928; 18533 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Harris County Flood Control District: correspondence, maps, 1958-1963; 18531 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Houston District Board of Missions and Church Extension: correspondence, 1937-1938; 18530 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Houston Lighting and Power Company: correspondence, maps, deeds, 1939-1962; 18529 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Hubbard, Ida Cochrum and Mary Ida: Humble Oil Stocks: correspondence, accounts, 1939-1964; 18528 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Humble Field: titles, deeds, 1902-1966; 18527 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Humble Oil and Refining Company: correspondence, deeds, 1914-1971; 18526 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Humble Oil and Refining Company: Report on the Power Supply for the East Texas Field, 1931; 18525 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Humble Oil and Refining Company: Valuation … as of charts, January 5, 1939:; 18524 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Humble Oil and Refining Company: Valuation … as of narrative and exhibits, January 5, 1939:; 18523 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - I: miscellaneous correspondence, 1939, 1961; 18522 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Income tax reports, 1922-1940; 18521 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Jackson, J. C.: correspondence, titles, deeds, 1943, 1948; 18520 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Joint Educational Commission, Methodist Schools: correspondence, 1933-1937; 18519 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Jones, Jesse H.: correspondence bond, 1923, 1931; 18518 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - K: miscellaneous correspondence, 1930-1962; 18517 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - L: miscellaneous correspondence, 1922-1964; 18516 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Lynd, J. H.: correspondence, 1936-1938; 18515 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - M: miscellaneous correspondence, titles, deeds, 1906-1971; 18514 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Methodist Brotherhood: correspondence, 1937-1962; 18513 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Methodist Conferences: correspondence, 1934-1938; 18512 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Methodist Home, Waco, Texas: correspondence, 1943-1966; 18511 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Methodist Homes for Older People, Houston, Texas: correspondence, maps, easement, deeds, 1962-1964; 18510 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Methodist Hospital, Houston, Texas: deeds, titles, statements, correspondence, 1926-1969; 18509 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Montrose Blvd. [3410], Houston, Texas: correspondence, deeds, accounts, clippings, 1911-1965; 18508 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1926-1932; 18507 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - N: miscellaneous correspondence, 1926-1958; 18506 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - National Bank of Commerce, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1926-1943; 18505 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - O: miscellaneous correspondence, 1913-1957; 18504 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oil Companies, minor, 1902-1943; 18503 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oklahoma tax records, 1922-1939; 18502 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - P: miscellaneous correspondence, 1903-1973; 18501 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Pano Tech Exploration Corporation: correspondence, 1955-1967; 18500 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Patents and correspondence concerning W. W. Fondren inventions, 1918-1927; 18499 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Q: miscellaneous correspondence, 1938; 18498 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - R: miscellaneous correspondence, titles, deeds, 1906-1971; 18497 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Rice Institute, Houston, Texas: athletic tickets, correspondence, 1926-1951; 18496 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Rice Institute, Houston, Texas: Fondren Library: correspondence, plans, 1946-1949; 18495 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - River Oaks Country Club, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1927-1937; 18494 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - S: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, bonds, stock certificates, 1906-1972; 18493 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Saint Paul's Methodist Church, Houston, Texas: correspondence, accounts, 1922-1968; 18492 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - San Jacinto Trust Company, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1929-1940; 18491 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Scarritt College for Christian Workers, Nashville, Tennessee: correspondence, 1942-1950; 18490 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Seaboard Life Insurance Company, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1925-1931; 18489 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Smith, A. Frank, Bishop: correspondence, accounts, 1931-1937; 18488 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas: correspondence, deeds, titles, accounts, 1919-1970; 18487 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas: Fondren Library: correspondence, deeds, titles, 1935-1970; 18486 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas: Fondren Science Building: deeds, titles, correspondence, 1946-1953; 18485 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Southern Methodist University, Dallas, Texas: Kirby Fig Farm, Algoa, Texas: correspondence, 1926-1937; 18484 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Southwestern University, Georgetown, Texas: correspondence, 1926-1952; 18483 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Sparkman, Lizzie and F. L.: deeds, titles, correspondence, 1912-1939; 18482 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Standard Oil Company: correspondence, 1920-1923; 18481 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - State Building and Loan Association: deeds, titles, accounts, correspondence, 1923-1936; 18480 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Sterett, Camp: correspondence, 1921-1934; 18479 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - T: miscellaneous correspondence, deeds, titles, 1909-1973; 18478 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Tabb's Bay Oil Company, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1938-1958; 18477 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Tax receipts (State, county, city):, 1907-1939; 18476 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Texaco: correspondence, 1921-1972; 18475 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Texas A & M College: correspondence, deeds, titles, 1951-1955; 18474 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Texas Hotel Supply Company, Houston, Texas: correspondence, stock certificates, 1928-1933; 18473 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Texas Methodist Foundation: correspondence, 1937-1938; 18472 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Tidewater Oil Company, Houston, Texas: correspondence, 1923-1938; 18471 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Trammell, A., H. L. and W. B.: deeds, correspondence, 1921-1937; 18470 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - U: miscellaneous correspondence, 1924-1938; 18469 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - University of Houston: correspondence, 1954-1967; 18468 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - V: miscellaneous correspondence, 1923-1971; 18467 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - W: miscellaneous correspondence, volt meter disc, deed, 1925-1964; 18466 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Westmoreland Ave. [401], Houston, Texas: construction contract, builder's account, views, 1905; 18465 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - YMCA, Houston, Texas: correspondence, photos, accounts, 1921-1943; 18464 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Unfoldered items, 18463 (Box 13)
- Series II: Bank books and ledgers, 142799
  - Bank Book: The National Bank of Commerce, Houston, Texas [W. W. Fondren], 1918-1939; 18462 (Box 13)
  - Bank Book (record of payments): The Union National Bank, Houston, Texas [W. W. Fondren], 1913-1923; 18461 (Box 13)
  - Cash Book [W. W. Fondren], 1925; 18460 (Box 13)
  - Cash Book, 1926-28; 18459 (Box 13)
  - Journal [W. W. Fondren], 1929-1938; 18458 (Box 13)
  - S. E. Ledger [W. W. Fondren], 1917-1922; 18457 (Box 13)
  - S. [E.] Ledger [Mr. Fondren's Personal Income], 1919-1920; 18456 (Box 13)
  - S. E. Ledger: W. W. Fondren, San Jacinto Trust Co. Account, [1927-1928]; 18455 (Box 13)
  - Post binder: W. W. Fondren Income beginning, 1923; 18454 (Box 13)
  - Post binder: Inactive Ledger [W. W. Fondren Estate and Ella F. Fondren], 1939-1971; 18453 (Box 13)
  - Standard Columnar Book [W. W. Fondren], 1929-1932; 18452 (Box 13)
  - Post binder: [miscellaneous accounts], 1918-1936; 18451 (Box 14)
  - Post binder: The Journal and Ledger Accounts of the Fondren Foundation, 1948-1969; 18450 (Box 14)